<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="outlines.xsl"?>

<outlines title="HTUTM 2">
    <section title="Conceptual and Non-conceptual minds">
    From the point of view of how they engage their objects, minds can be divided into two:

    <types>
            <type>
        1	Conceptual minds
            </type>
            <type>
        2	Non-conceptual minds
            </type>
    </types>

    <definition>
    The definition of conceptual mind is a thought that apprehends its object through a generic image.
    </definition>

    There are five types of object:
    <types>
        <type>
        1	Appearing object
        </type>
        <type>
        2	Observed object
        </type>
        <type>
        3	Engaged object
        </type>
        <type>
        4	Apprehended object
        </type>
        <type>
        5	Conceived object
        </type>
    </types>
    <definition>
    The definition of generic image is the appearing object of a conceptual mind.
    </definition>

    There are three types of conceptual mind:
    <types>
        <type>
    1	Conceptual minds that perceive the generic image of an object mainly through the force of listening or reading
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Conceptual minds that perceive the generic image of an object mainly through the force of contemplating the meaning of that object
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Conceptual minds that perceive the generic image of an object mainly through the force of previous imprints
        </type>
    </types>
    There is also a twofold division of conceptual mind:
    <types>
        <type>
    1	Correct conceptual minds
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Wrong conceptual minds
        </type>
    </types>

    <definition>
    The definition of non-conceptual mind is a cognizer to which its object appears clearly without being mixed with a generic image.
    </definition>

    There are two types of non-conceptual mind:
    <types>
        <type>
    1	Sense awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Non-conceptual mental awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>

    There are three types of non-conceptual mental awareness:
    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-conceptual mental direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Yogic direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Non-conceptual mental awarenesses that are neither of these two
        </type>
    </types>

    There is another twofold division of non-conceptual mind:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Correct non-conceptual minds
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Wrong non-conceptual minds
        </type>
    </types>


    </section>
    <section title="Sense and Mental Awareness">
    From the point of view of their uncommon dominant condition, minds can be divided into two:

    <types>
        <type>
        1	Sense awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
        2	Mental awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>
    The definition of sense awareness is an awareness that is developed in dependence upon its uncommon dominant condition, a sense power possessing form.

    There are five types of sense awareness:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Eye awareness
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Ear awareness
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Nose awareness
        </type>
        <type>
    4	Tongue awareness
        </type>
        <type>
    5	Body awareness
        </type>
    </types>
        <definition>
            The definition of eye awareness is an awareness that is developed in dependence upon its uncommon dominant condition, an eye sense power. This definition can be applied to the other four sense awarenesses by changing the uncommon dominant condition to the ear sense power, the nose sense power, the tongue sense power, or the body sense power.
        </definition>

        <definition>
            The definition of dominant condition of sense awareness is that which principally assists in the development of a sense awareness.
        </definition>

    There are two types of dominant condition:
    <types>
        <type>
        1	Common dominant condition
        </type>
        <type>
        2	Uncommon dominant condition
        </type>
    </types>
        <definition>
            The definition of mental awareness is an awareness that is developed in dependence upon its uncommon dominant condition, a mental power.
        </definition>

        <definition>
            The definition of mental power is a mentality that principally functions directly to produce the uncommon aspect of a mental awareness.
        </definition>

    There are two types of mental awareness:
    <types>
        <type>
    1	Conceptual mental awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Non-conceptual mental awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>
    There is also a threefold division of mental awareness:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-virtuous mental awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Virtuous mental awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Neutral mental awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>

    </section>
    <section title="Direct Perceivers">
    From the point of view of enabling us to understand how we can become a Superior being by attaining yogic direct perceivers, minds can be divided into seven:
    <types>
        <type>
    1	Direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Subsequent cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Re-cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    4	Correct beliefs
        </type>
        <type>
    5	Non-ascertaining perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    6	Non-deluded doubt
        </type>
        <type>
    7	Wrong awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>
        <definition>
    The definition of direct perceiver is a cognizer that apprehends its object correctly and directly.
        </definition>

    There are three types of direct perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Mental direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Yogic direct perceivers
        </type>
    </types>

        <definition>
    The definition of sense direct perceiver is a direct perceiver that is generated in dependence upon its uncommon dominant condition, a sense power possessing form.
        </definition>

    There are five types of sense direct perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Eye sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Ear sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Nose sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    4	Tongue sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    5	Body sense direct perceivers
        </type>
    </types>

    There is also a threefold division of sense direct perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Sense direct perceivers that are valid cognizers but not re-cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Sense direct perceivers that are both valid cognizers and re-cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Sense direct perceivers that are non-ascertaining perceivers
        </type>
    </types>

        <definition>
    The definition of mental direct perceiver is a direct perceiver that is generated in dependence upon its uncommon dominant condition, a mental power.
        </definition>

    There are three types of mental direct perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Mental direct perceivers induced by sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Mental direct perceivers induced by meditation
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Mental direct perceivers that are induced neither by sense direct perceivers nor by meditation
        </type>
    </types>

    There are five types of mental direct perceiver induced by sense direct perceivers: these are mental direct perceivers apprehending forms, sounds, smells, tastes and tactile objects.

        <definition>
    The definition of yogic direct perceiver is a direct perceiver that realizes the true nature of phenomena directly, in dependence upon its uncommon dominant condition, a concentration that is a union of tranquil abiding and superior seeing.
        </definition>

    There are two types of yogic direct perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Yogic direct perceivers in the continuum of Hinayanists
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Yogic direct perceivers in the continuum of Mahayanists
        </type>
    </types>

    There is also a threefold division of yogic direct perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Yogic direct perceivers that are paths of seeing
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Yogic direct perceivers that are paths of meditation
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Yogic direct perceivers that are Paths of No More Learning
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Subsequent Cognizers">
        <definition>
    The definition of subsequent cognizer is a completely reliable cognizer whose object is realized in direct dependence upon a conclusive reason.
        </definition>
        <definition>
    The definition of conclusive reason is a reason that is qualified by the three modes.
        </definition>
    There are three types of subsequent cognizer from the point of view of the type of reason upon which they depend:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Subsequent cognizers through the power of fact
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Subsequent cognizers through belief
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Subsequent cognizers through renown
        </type>
    </types>

    There is also a twofold division of subsequent cognizer from the point of view of how they are generated:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Subsequent cognizers arisen from listening or reading
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Subsequent cognizers arisen from contemplation
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Re-congnizers">
        <definition>
    The definition of re-cognizer is a cognizer that realizes what has already been realized through the force of a previous valid cognizer.
        </definition>
    There are two types of re-cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-conceptual re-cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Conceptual re-cognizers
        </type>
    </types>

    There are three types of non-conceptual re-cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Re-cognizers that are sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Re-cognizers that are mental direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Re-cognizers that are yogic direct perceivers
        </type>
    </types>

    There are two types of conceptual re-cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Conceptual re-cognizers induced by direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Conceptual re-cognizers induced by subsequent cognizers
        </type>
    </types>

    There are three types of conceptual re-cognizer induced by direct perceivers:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Conceptual re-cognizers induced by sense direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Conceptual re-cognizers induced by mental direct perceivers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Conceptual re-cognizers induced by yogic direct perceivers
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Correct Beliefs">
        <definition>
    The definition of correct belief is a non-valid cognizer that realizes its conceived object.
        </definition>

    There are two types of correct belief:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Correct beliefs that do not depend upon a reason
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Correct beliefs that depend upon a reason
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Non-ascertaining Perceivers">
        <definition>
    The definition of non-ascertaining perceiver is a cognizer to which a phenomenon that is its engaged object appears clearly without being ascertained.
        </definition>

    There are two types of non-ascertaining perceiver:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-ascertaining sense awareness
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Non-ascertaining mental awareness
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Non-deluded Doubts">
    <definition>
    The definition of non-deluded doubt is a doubt that does not disturb our peace of mind and gives rise to positive results.
        </definition>
    There are two types of non-deluded doubt:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-deluded doubts with respect to ultimate truth
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Non-deluded doubts with respect to conventional truths
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Wrong Awareness">
        <definition>
    The definition of wrong awareness is a cognizer that is mistaken with respect to its engaged object.
        </definition>

    There are two types of wrong awareness:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-conceptual wrong awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Conceptual wrong awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>

    There are two types of non-conceptual wrong awareness:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Wrong sense awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Wrong non-conceptual mental awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>

    A wrong sense awareness can be mistaken with respect to its object in any of seven different ways: being mistaken with respect to its object’s shape, colour, activity, number, time, measurement or entity.

    There are two types of conceptual wrong awareness:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Intellectually-formed wrong awarenesses
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Innate wrong awarenesses
        </type>
    </types>

    There are two causes of wrong awareness:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Ultimate causes
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Temporary causes
        </type>
    </types>

    There are four temporary causes of wrong sense awareness:


    <types>
        <type>
    1	A deceptive quality of the object
        </type>
        <type>
    2	A deceptive situation
        </type>
        <type>
    3	A defective sense power
        </type>
        <type>
    4	A fault in the preceding awareness
        </type>
    </types>

    </section>
    <section title="Valid and Non-valid Cognizers">
    There are three ways in which the term ‘valid’ can be applied:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Valid Teachers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Valid teachings
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Valid cognizers
        </type>
    </types>

        <definition>
    The definition of valid Teacher is a Teacher who knows fully and without error what objects are to be abandoned and what objects are to be practised, and who, out of compassion, reveals this knowledge to others.
        </definition>
        <definition>
    The definition of valid teaching is an instruction that principally explains without error the objects to be abandoned and how to abandon them, and the objects to be practised and how to practise them.
        </definition>
        <definition>
    The definition of valid cognizer is a cognizer that is non- deceptive with respect to its engaged object.
        </definition>
    There are two types of valid cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	A valid cognizer that is non-deceptive with respect to its manifest object
        </type>
        <type>
    2	A valid cognizer that is non-deceptive with respect to its hidden object
        </type>
    </types>

        <definition>
    The definition of manifest object is an object whose initial realization by a valid cognizer does not depend upon logical reasons.
        </definition>
        <definition>
    The definition of hidden object is an object whose initial realization by a valid cognizer depends upon correct logical reasons.
        </definition>
        <definition>
    The definition of direct valid cognizer is a non-deceptive cognizer that realizes its object directly.
        </definition>
    There are three types of direct valid cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Valid sense direct cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Valid mental direct cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Valid yogic direct cognizers
        </type>
    </types>
        <definition>
    The definition of subsequent valid cognizer is a non-deceptive cognizer that realizes its hidden object by depending upon a conclusive reason.
        </definition>
    There are three types of subsequent valid cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Subsequent valid cognizers through the power of fact
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Subsequent valid cognizers through belief
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Subsequent valid cognizers through renown
        </type>
    </types>

        <definition>
    The definition of non-valid cognizer is a cognizer that is deceptive with respect to its engaged object.
        </definition>
    There are two types of non-valid cognizer:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Non-conceptual non-valid cognizers
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Conceptual non-valid cognizers
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
    <section title="Meditation">
        <definition>
    The definition of meditation is a mind that is single-pointedly focused on a virtuous object and whose function is to make the mind peaceful and calm.
        </definition>
    There is a threefold division of meditation:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Meditation of a person of initial scope
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Meditation of a person of middling scope
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Meditation of a person of great scope
        </type>
    </types>

    There are five meditations of a person of initial scope:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Meditation on the preciousness of our human life
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Meditation on death
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Meditation on the dangers of lower rebirth
        </type>
        <type>
    4	Meditation on going for refuge
        </type>
        <type>
    5	Meditation on karma
        </type>
    </types>

    There are four meditations of a person of middling scope:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Meditation on renunciation
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Meditation on our determination to recognize, reduce and abandon our self-grasping ignorance, the root of samsaric rebirth
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Meditation on our determination to enter and make progress on the path to liberation
        </type>
        <type>
    4	Meditation on the ultimate truth of cessation
        </type>
    </types>

    There are five meditations of a person of great scope:

    <types>
        <type>
    1	Meditation on cherishing all living beings
        </type>
        <type>
    2	Meditation on universal compassion
        </type>
        <type>
    3	Meditation on the supreme good heart, bodhichitta
        </type>
        <type>
    4	Meditation on our determination and promise to sincerely practise the six perfections
        </type>
        <type>
    5	Meditation on training in yogic direct perceivers
        </type>
    </types>
    </section>
</outlines>

