<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<htutm>
 <intro>
 The explanation of How to Understand the Mind begins
 with an explanation of what is our mind, how the mind is able to move,
 and the different levels of mind
</intro>


 <definition>The definition of the mind is something whose nature is empty
 like space, always lacking form, shape and colour, and whose function
 is to perceive or understand objects.
</definition>


 From the point of view of its different levels,
 the mind is divided into three:
<types>
 <type>
 The gross mind,
 </type>
<type>
 The subtle mind
</type>
<type>
 The very subtle mind
</type>
</types>

From the point of view of its function, the mind can be divided into primary minds and mental factors.

<definition>The definition of primary mind is a cognizer that principally apprehends the mere entity of an object.
</definition>

Primary minds, mentality and consciousness are synonyms.

There are six types of primary mind:
 <types>
    <type>
 Eye consciousness
    </type>
    <type>
 Ear consciousness
    </type>
    <type>
 Nose consciousness
    </type>
    <type>
 Tongue consciousness
    </type>
    <type>
 Body consciousness
    </type>
    <type>
 Mental consciousness
    </type>
</types>

 <definition>The definition of mental factor is a cognizer that principally apprehends a particular attribute of an object. </definition>

 A primary mind and its mental factors possess five similarities:

  <types>
  <type>Basis </type><type>
 Object </type><type>
 Aspect </type><type>
 Time </type><type>
 Substance  </type>
  </types>

 There are fifty one mental factors which are divided into six groups:

  <types>
  <type>The five all-accompanying mental factors </type><type>
 The five object-ascertaining mental factors </type><type>
 The eleven virtuous mental factors </type><type>
 The six root delusions </type><type>
 The twenty secondary delusions </type><type>
 The four changeable mental factors          </type>
  </types>

<the-five-all-accompanying-mental-factors>

 The five all-accompanying mental factors are:

  <types>
  <type>Feeling </type><type>
 Discrimination </type><type>
 Intention </type><type>
 Contact </type><type>
 Attention      </type>
  </types>

<feeling>
 <definition>The definition of feeling is a mental factor that functions to experience pleasant, unpleasant or neutral objects.      </definition>

 There are three types of feelins:

  <types>
  <type>Pleasant feelings </type><type>
 Unpleasant feelings </type><type>
 Neutral feelings       </type>
  </types>

 There is also a twofold division of feeling from the point of view of their uncommon dominant condition:

   <types>
   <type> Bodily feelings </type><type>
  Mental feelings  </type>
   </types>

  There is another twofold division of feeling from the point of view of their nature:

   <types>
   <type>Contaminated feelings </type><type>
  Uncontaminated feelings  </type>
   </types>
</feeling>

<discrimination>
  <definition>The definition of discrimination is a mental factor that functions to apprehend the uncommon sign of an object.  </definition>

  There are six types of discrimination:

   <types>
   <type>Discrimination associated with eye consciousness </type><type>
  Discrimination associated with ear consciousness </type><type>
  Discrimination associated with nose consciousness </type><type>
  Discrimination associated with tongue consciousness </type><type>
  Discrimination associated with body consciousness </type><type>
  Discrimination associated with mental consciousness  </type>
   </types>

  There is also a twofold division of discrimination:

   <types>
   <type> Mistaken discriminations </type><type>
  Non-mistaken discriminations    </type>
   </types>

  There is another twofold division of discriminations:

   <types>
   <type>Clear discriminations </type><type>
  Unclear discriminations  </type>
   </types>
</discrimination>

<intention>
  <definition>The definition of intention is a mental factor that functions to focus its primary mind on an object.  </definition>

 There are three types of intention:

   <types>
   <type> Non-virtuous intentions </type><type>
  Virtious intentions </type><type>
  Neutral intentions   </type>
   </types>

  There are three types of non-virtuous actions:

   <types>
   <type>Non-virtuous bodily actions </type><type>
  Non-virtuous verbal actions </type><type>
  Non-virtuous mental actions   </type>
   </types>

  There is another threefold division of intention:

 <types>
 <type>Meritorious actions </type><type>
Non-meritorious actions </type><type>
Unfluctuating objects  </type>
 </types>

There is a threefold division of both meritorious and non-meritorious actions:
those that are throwing karma, those that are completing karma, and those that are karma
whose results are experienced in the same life.
</intention>

<contact>
<definition>The definition of contact is a mental factor that functions to perceive its object as a pleasant, unpleasant or neutral.      </definition>

There are six types of contact:

   <types>
   <type>Contact associated with eye consciousness </type><type>
  Contact associated with ear consciousness </type><type>
  Contact associated with nose consciousness </type><type>
  Contact associated with tongue consciousness </type><type>
  Contact associated with body consciousness </type><type>
  Contact associated with mental consciousness   </type>
   </types>
</contact>
<attention>
  <definition>The definition of attention is a mental factor that functions to focus the mind on a particular attribute of an object.  </definition>

  There are two types of attention:

   <types>
   <type>Correct attention </type><type>
  Incorrect attention    </type>
   </types>

  There is another twofold division of attention:

   <types>
   <type>Appropriate attention </type><type>
  Inappropriate attention </type>
   </types>
</attention>
</the-five-all-accompanying-mental-factors>


<the-five-object-ascertaining-mental-factors>
  The five object-ascertaining mental factors are:

   <types>
   <type>Aspiration </type><type>
  Firm apprehension </type><type>
  Mindfulness </type><type>
  Concentration </type><type>
  Wisdom           </type>
   </types>


<aspiration>
  <definition>The definition of aspiration is a mental factor that focuses on a desired object and takes an interest in it.  </definition>

  There are four types of aspiration:

   <types>
   <type>Wishing to meet an object </type><type>
  Wish not to be separated from an object </type><type>
  Wishing to obtain an object </type><type>
  Wishing to be released form an object </type>
   </types>

  Each of these can be virtuous, non-virtuous or neutral, depending upon its motivation.

  There is also a twofold division of aspiration:

   <types>
   <type> Mistaken aspirations </type><type>
  Non-mistaken aspirations     </type>
   </types>
</aspiration>

<Firm-apprehension>
  <definition>The definition of firm apprehension is a mental factor that makes its primary apprehend its object firmly.  </definition>

  There are two types of firm apprehension:

   <types>
   <type> Correct firm apprehensions </type><type>
  Mistaken firm apprehensions </type>
   </types>
</Firm-apprehension>

<mindfulness>
  <definition>The definition of mindfulness is a mental factor that functions not to forget the object realized by the primary mind. </definition>

  There are two types of mindfulness:

   <types>
   <type>New mindfulness </type><type>
  Old mindfulness </type>
   </types>

  There is another twofold division of mindfulness:

   <types>
   <type>Mindfulness with movements of mental sinking and excitement </type><type>
  Mindfulness without movements of mental sinking and excitement </type>
   </types>
</mindfulness>

<concentration>
  <definition>The definition of concentration is a mental factor that makes its primary mind remain on its object single-pointedly.</definition>

  There are three ways of dividing virtuous concentration: from the point of view of realm, from the point of view of its
  effect and from the point of view of its object.

  There are nine levels of concentration from the point of view of realm:

 <types>
 <type>Concentration of the desire realm </type><type>
Concentration of the the first form realm </type><type>
Concentration of the the second form realm </type><type>
Concentration of the the third form realm </type><type>
Concentration of the the fourth form realm </type><type>
Concentration of infinite space </type><type>
Concentration of infinite consciousness </type><type>
Concentration of nothingness </type><type>
Concentration of the peak of samsara </type>
 </types>

There are nine levels of desire realm concentration:

 <types>
 <type>Placing the mind </type><type>
Continual placement </type><type>
Replacement </type><type>
Close placement </type><type>
Controlling </type><type>
Pacifying </type><type>
Completely pacifying </type><type>
Single-pointedness </type><type>
Placement in equipoise </type>
 </types>

There are two types of concentration form the point of view of their effect:

 <types>
 <type>Mundane concentrations </type><type>
Supramundane concentrations </type>
 </types>

There is another twofold division of concentration from the point of view of its object:

 <types>
 <type>Concentration observing conventional objects </type><type>
Concentration observing ultimate objects </type>
 </types>
</concentration>
<wisdom>
<definition>The definition of wisdom is a virtuous, intelligent mind that makes its primary mind realize a meaningful object. </definition>

There are three types of wisdom:

 <types>
 <type>Wisdom arisen from listening or reading </type><type>
Wisdom arisen from contemplation </type><type>
Wisdom arisen from meditation </type>
 </types>

There is also a sevenfold division of wisdom:

 <types>
 <type>Great wisdom </type><type>
Clear wisdom </type><type>
Quick wisdom </type><type>
Profound wisdom </type><type>
The wisdom of expounding dharma </type><type>
The wisdom of spiritual debate </type><type>
The wisdom of composing dharma books</type>
 </types>
</wisdom>
</the-five-object-ascertaining-mental-factors>
<The-eleven-virtuous-mental-factors>
The eleven virtuous mental factors are:

 <types>
 <type>Faith </type><type>
Sense of shame </type><type>
Consideration of others </type><type>
Non-attachment </type><type>
Non-hatred </type><type>
Non-ignorance </type><type>
Effort </type><type>
Mental suppleness </type><type>
Conscientiousness </type><type>
Equanimity </type><type>
Non-harmfulness </type>
 </types>



<Faith>
<definition>The definition of faith is a mental factor that functions principally to eliminate non-faith.</definition>

There are three types of faith:

 <types>
 <type>Believing faith </type><type>
Admiring faith </type><type>
Wishing faith  </type>
 </types>

</Faith>

<Sense-of-shame>

<definition>The definition of sense of shame is a mental factor that functions to avoid inappropriate actions for reasons
that concern ourself.                                                   </definition>

There are three types of sense of shame.

 <types>
 <type>Sense of shame that restrains is from inappropriate bodily actions </type><type>
Sense of shame that restrains is from inappropriate verbal actions </type><type>
Sense of shame that restrains is from inappropriate mental actions  </type>
 </types>

There is also a twofold division of sense of shame:

 <types>
 <type>Sense of shame that restrains us from inappropriate actions out of concern simply for ourself </type><type>
Sense of shame that restrains us from inappropriate actions out of concern for the specific undesirable results for ourself  </type>
 </types>
</Sense-of-shame>

<Consideration-for-others>
<definition>The definition of consideration for others is a mental factor that functions to avoid inappropriate actions for reasons
that concern others.                                                                                                  </definition>

There are three types of consideration for others:

 <types>
 <type>Consideration for others that restrains is from inappropriate bodily actions </type><type>
Consideration for others that restrains is from inappropriate verbal actions </type><type>
Consideration for others that restrains is from inappropriate mental actions </type>
 </types>

There is also a twofold division of consideration for others:

 <types>
 <type>Consideration for others that restrains us from inappropriate actions out of concern simply for otheres </type><type>
Consideration for others that restrains us from inappropriate actions out of concern for the specific undesirable results for others </type>
 </types>

<definition>The definition of non-attachment is a mental factor that functions as the direct opponent of attachment.  </definition>

</Consideration-for-others>

<Non-attachment>
There are three types of non-attachment:

 <types>
 <type>Non-attachment to samsaric places </type><type>
Non-attachment to samsaric enjoyments </type><type>
Non-attachment to samsaric bodies  </type>
 </types>

There is another threefold division of non-attachment

 <types>
 <type>Non-attachment to this life </type><type>
Non-attachment to samsara </type><type>
Non-attachment to solitary peace  </type>
 </types>
</Non-attachment>

<Non-hatred>
<definition>The definition of non-hatred is a mental factor that functions as the direct opponent of hatred.</definition>

There are three types of non-hatred:

 <types>
 <type>Non-hatred towards those who harm us </type><type>
Non-hatred towards inanimate objects that cause us suffering </type><type>
Non-hatred towards resultant suffering </type>
 </types>
</Non-hatred>

<Non-ignorance>
<definition>The definition of non-ignorance is a mental factor that functions as the direct opponent of ignorance. </definition>

There are four types of non-ignorance:

 <types>
 <type>Non-ignorance arisen from listening reading </type><type>
Non-ignorance arisen from contemplation </type><type>
Non-ignorance arisen from meditation </type><type>
Non-ignorance arisen from imprints </type>
 </types>

</Non-ignorance>

<effort>

<definition>The definition of effort is a mental factor that makes its primary mind delight in virtue. </definition>

There are four types of effort:

 <types>
 <type>Armour-like effort </type><type>
Effort of non-discouragement </type><type>
Effort application </type><type>
Effort of non-satisfaction  </type>
 </types>

There is also a fivefold division of effort:

 <types>
 <type>Armour-like effort </type><type>
Effort of non-discouragement </type><type>
Effort application </type><type>
Effort of non-satisfaction </type><type>
Effort of irreversibility  </type>
 </types>

There is also a threefold division of effort:

 <types>
 <type>Armour-like effort </type><type>
Effort of gathering virtuous Dharmas </type><type>
Effort of benefiting others  </type>
 </types>

There are four powers:

 <types>
 <type>The power of aspiration </type><type>
The power of steadfastness </type><type>
The power of joy </type><type>
The power of rejection   </type>
 </types>

</effort>

<Mental-suppleness>
<definition>The definition of mental suppleness is a flexibility of mind induced by virtuous concentration. </definition>

There are two types of mental suppleness:

 <types>
 <type>Subtle mental suppleness </type><type>
Gross mental suppleness </type>
 </types>
</Mental-suppleness>

<Conscientiousness>

<definition>The definition of conscientiousness is a mental factor that, in dependence upon effort,
cherishes what is virtuous and gueards the mind from delusion and non-virtue.      </definition>

There are two types of conscientiousness:

 <types>
 <type>Conscientiousness that is a virtuous root of mundane paths </type><type>
Conscientiousness that is a virtuous root of supramundane paths </type>
 </types>
</Conscientiousness>

<Equanimity>
<definition>The definition of equanimity is a mental factor that functions to keep the primary mind free from mental sinking and
mental excitement.                                      </definition>

There are three types of equanimity:

 <types>
 <type>Equanimity that requires gross effort </type><type>
Equanimity that requires subtle effort </type><type>
Equanimity that requires no effort </type>
 </types>
</Equanimity>

<Non-harmfulness>
<definition>The definition of non-harmfulness is a mental factor that wishes sentient beings not to suffer.  </definition>

There two types of non-harmfulness, or compassion:

 <types>
 <type>Compassion wishing sentient beings to be free from suffering </type><type>
Compassion wishing sentient beings to be free from the causes of suffering </type>
 </types>

There is another twofold division of compassion:

 <types>
 <type>Mere compassion </type><type>
Superior compassion  </type>
 </types>
</Non-harmfulness>

</The-eleven-virtuous-mental-factors>


<definition>The definition of virtue is a phenomenon that functions as a main cause of happiness.  </definition>

There are five types of virtue:

 <types>
 <type>Natural virtue </type><type>
Virtue by association </type><type>
Virtue by motivation </type><type>
Virtue by subsequent relation </type><type>
Ultimate virtue </type>
 </types>

<definition>The definition of non-virtue is a phenomenon that functions as a main cause of suffering.  </definition>

There are five types of non-virtue:

 <types>
 <type>Natural non-virtue </type><type>
Virtue by association </type><type>
Virtue by motivation </type><type>
Virtue by subsequent relation </type><type>
Ultimate non-virtue  </type>
 </types>

<definition>The definition of delusion is a mental factor that arises from inappropriate attention and that functions to make the
mind unpeaceful and uncontrolled.                         </definition>

There are six causes of delusion:

 <types>
 <type>The seed </type><type>
The object </type><type>
Inappropriate attention </type><type>
Familiarity </type><type>
Distraction and being influenced by others </type><type>
Bad habits </type>
 </types>

There are three types of delusion from the point of view of realm:

 <types>
 <type>Delusions of the desire realm </type><type>
Delusions of the form realm </type><type>
Delusions of the formless realm </type>
 </types>

There are nine levels, from big-big to small-small, of eah of the delusions of the desire realm, and of each
of the delusions of each level of the form and formless realms, making eighty-one levels of delusion in all.

There is also a twofold division of delusion from the point of view of their cause:

 <types>
 <type>Innate delusion </type><type>
Intellectually-formed delusions</type>
 </types>

There is another twofold division of delusion from the point of view of entity:

 <types>
 <type>Root delusions </type><type>
Secondary delusions      </type>
 </types>


<The-six-root-delusions>
The six root delusions are:

 <types>
 <type>Desirous attachment </type><type>
Anger </type><type>
Deluded pride </type><type>
Ignorance </type><type>
Deluded doubt </type><type>
Deluded view </type>
 </types>

<deisrous-attachment>
<definition>The definition of desirous attachment is a deluded mental factor that observes its contaminated object, regards it as a
cause of happiness, and wishes for it.                       </definition>

There are three types of desirous attachment from the point of view of time.

 <types>
 <type>Desirous attachment to past objects </type><type>
Desirous attachment to present objects </type><type>
Desirous attachment to future objects </type>
 </types>

From the point of view of entity, desirous attachment can be divided into three - big, middling and small - or into
eighty-one - the nine levels of desirous attachment of each of the nine realms. These are all included within three:

 <types>
 <type>Desire realm desirous attachment </type><type>
Form realm desirous attachment </type><type>
Formless realm desirous attachment  </type>
 </types>

There is another threefold division of desirous attachment from the point of view of its object:

 <types>
 <type>Desirous attachment to samsaric places </type><type>
Desirous attachment to samsaric enjoyments </type><type>
Desirous attachment to samsaric bodies </type>
 </types>
</deisrous-attachment>

<anger>
<definition>The definition of anger is a deluded mental factor that observes its contaminated object, exagerates its bad qualities,
considers it to be undesirable, and wishes to harm it.     </definition>

 There are nine types of anger from the point of view of entity, from big-big to small-small.

 There is another ninefold division of anger from the point of view of how it is generated:

  <types>
  <type>Anger towards someone or something that harmed us in the past </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that is harming us now </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that might harm us in the future </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that harmed our friends or relatives in the past </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that is harming our friends or relatives now </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that might harm our friends or relative in the future </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that helped our enemy in the past </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that is helping our enemy now </type><type>
 Anger towards someone or something that might help our enemy in the future</type>
  </types>
</anger>

<deluded-pride>
<definition>The definition of deluded pride is a deluded mental factor that, through considering and exaggerating one's own good
qualities or possessions, feels arrogant.  </definition>

There are seven types of deluded pride:

 <types>
 <type>Pride over inferiors </type><type>
Pride over equals </type><type>
Pride over superiors </type><type>
Pride in identity </type><type>
Pretentious pride </type><type>
Emulating pride </type><type>
Wrong pride  </type>
 </types>
</deluded-pride>

<ignorance>
<definition>The definition of ignorance is a mental factor that is confused about the nature of an object and functions to induce
wrong awareness, doubt and other delusions.        </definition>

There are two types of ignorance:

 <types>
 <type>Ignorance of conventional truths </type><type>
Ignorance of ultimate truths </type>
 </types>

There is another twofold division of ignorance:

 <types>
 <type>Ignorance of actions and their effects, or karma </type><type>
Ignorance of emptiness </type>
 </types>
</ignorance>

<deluded-doubt>
<definition>The definition of deluded doubt is a two-pointedness of mind that interferes with the attainment of liberation
or enlightenment.                                    </definition>

There are three type of doubt in general:

 <types>
 <type>Doubts tending towards the truth </type><type>
Doubts tending away from the truth </type><type>
Balanced doubts </type>
 </types>
</deluded-doubt>

<deluded-view>
<definition>The definition of deluded view is a view that functions to obstruct the attainment of liberation.  </definition>

There are five types of deluded view:

 <types>
 <type>View of the transitory collection </type><type>
Extreme view </type><type>
Holding false views as supreme </type><type>
Holding wrong moral discipline and conduct as supreme </type><type>
Wrong view             </type>
 </types>
</deluded-view>

<view-of-the-transitory-collection>
<definition>The definition of view of the transitory collection is a type of self-grasping of persons that grasps our own I as
being an inherently existent I.                                                   </definition>

There are two types of view of the transitory collection:

 <types>
 <type>View of the transitory collection conceiving I </type><type>
View of the transitory collection conceiving mine </type>
 </types>

There is another twofold division of view of the transitory collection:

 <types>
 <type>Innate view of the transitory collection </type><type>
Intellectually-formed view of the transitory collection </type>
 </types>

There are twenty intellectually-formed views of the transitory collection, four in relation to each of the five
aggregates.
</view-of-the-transitory-collection>
<extreme-view>
<definition>The definition of extreme view is an exaggerated incorrect view.    </definition>

 There are two types of extreme view: the extreme view of existence, and the extreme view of non-existence.
</extreme-view>

 <definition>The definition of holding false views as supreme is a deluded view that believes our own or others' incorrect views are
 supreme views.                     </definition>

 <definition>The definition of holding wrong moral discipline and conduct as supreme is a deluded view that holds any wrong moral
 discipline or conduct to be correct and considers it to be superior to other forms of moral discipline or conduct. </definition>

 <definition>The definition of wrong view is an intellectually-formed wrong awareness that denies the existence of an object that it
 is necessary to understand to attain liberation or enlightenment. </definition>

</The-six-root-delusions>

</htutm>

