<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="outlines.xsl"?>

<outlines title="MB">
    <section title="Ultimate Bodhichitta.">

        <section title="Training in Ultimate Bodhichitta">
            <definition>Actual ultimate bodhichitta is a wisdom that directly realizes emptiness motivated by bodhichitta.</definition>

            <p>The knowledge of emptiness is superior to any other knowledge.</p>

        </section>



        <section title="What is Emptiness?">
            Emptiness is the way things really are. It is the way things exist as opposed the the way they appear.
        </section>


        <section title="The Emptiness of our Body">
        <p>
        There are two ways of searching for an object - conventional search and ultimate search.
        </p>
            
        <p>
        Searching for the body that we grasp - it must exist amongst its parts or outside its parts. There is no third possibility.
        If a part of our body was our body then we would have many bodies. The body is the part-possessor.
        </p>

        <p>
        The collection of the parts of our body cannot be the body. A Collection of parts cannot magically transform into the part possessor - the body.
        If we could find the body as the collection of its parts - then we could remove all its parts and be left with the body.
        </p>

        <p>
        This non-existence of the body that we normally see is the emptiness of our body - the true nature of our body.
        </p>

        <p>
        It is perhaps less confusing to simply say that for a mind that directly sees the truth, emptiness, there is no body. A body exists only for an ordinary mind to which a body appears.
        </p>

        </section>
        <section title="The Emptiness of our Mind">
            <p>
                Our mind is a continuum that is merely imputed upon a collection of many factors - e.g. our primary mind has five parts - its five all-accompanying mental factors.
            </p>
        <p>
        All phenomena that appear to my mind are the nature of my mind and my mind is the nature of emptiness.
        </p>
        <p>
        This way of meditating on emptiness is more profound then the meditation on the emptiness of our body.
        </p>
        </section>
        <section title="The Emptiness of our I">

        If the I exists in the way it appears then it must exist as one of four possibilities:

        <list>
            <item>as the body</item>
            <item>as the mind</item>
            <item>as the collection of the body and mind</item>
            <item>or as something separate from the our body and mind.</item>
        </list>

        In truth, our self and other phenomena that exist as mere imputation is the ultimate nature of our self and other phenomena, not the conventional nature.
        </section>
        <section title="The Emptiness which is Empty of Eight Extremes">
            <list>
                <item>Production/Disintegration.</item>
                <item>Impermanence/Permanence.</item>
                <item>Going/Coming.</item>
                <item>Singularity/Plurality.</item>
            </list>
        </section>
        <section title="Conventional and Ultimate Truths">
        <p>
            Whatever exists is either a conventional truth or an ultimate truth.
        </p>
        <p>
            Conventional truths are false objects because the way they appear and the way they exist do not correspond.
        </p>
        <p>
            Although conventional truths are false, they do exist because they are realised by a valid mind.
        </p>
            <p>
            Conventional truths can be divided into:
            <list>
                <item>Gross conventional truths - depend upon their parts, causes, basis of imputation.</item>
                <item>Subtle conventional truths - existing merely as imputation by thought.</item>
            </list>
            </p>
        <p>
            Strictly speaking, truth, ultimate truth and emptiness are synonyms because conventional truths are not real truths but false objects.
        </p>

            <p>When we have realised the mere absence of the eight extremes then we have realised the emptiness of all
                phenomena.
            </p>


            <p>The meditation on the emptiness of produced phenomena(our self who was born in dependence of causes and
                conditions.. ) is called space-like meditative equipoise on emptiness.
            </p>


            If we are successful then during our meditation we are free from manifest self-grapsing.
        </section>
        <section title="The Union of the Two Truths">

        <definition>
            The union of the two truths means that the conventional truths such as our body and ultimate truths such as the emptiness of our body are the same nature
        </definition>
        <p>
            When our body appears to us we see both our body and the inherently existent body simultaneously. This is dualistic appearance which is subtle mistaken appearance.
        </p>

        There are two principal benefits of understanding that all emptinesses are the same nature:
        <list>
            <item>In the meditation session our mind will mix with emptiness more easily.</item>
            <item>In the meditation break we shall be able to see all appearances as equal manifestations of their emptiness.</item>
        </list>

        <p>The emptiness of the body, mind and I are the same nature and are distinguishable only by their conventional bases.</p>

        <p>For a qualified meditator single-pointedely absorbed in emptiness there is no difference between production/disintegration, impermanence/permanence, going/coming, singualrity/plurality.
        This realisation is called the yoga or equalizing samsara and nirvana.
        </p>


        </section>



        <section title="The Practice of Emptiness in our Daily Activities">
            <p>When we are familiar with emptiness the very fact that things appear clearly will remind us that they are not inherently existent.
            Knowing that whatever appears to our mind is mere appearance, when attractive objects appear we shall not grasp at them and develop attachment, and when unattractive objects appear we shall not grasp at them and develop aversion.
            </p>

            <p>
                Since our self grasping keeps us bound to samsara and is the source of all our problems, meditation on emptiness is the universal solution to all our problems.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="A Simple Training in Ultimate Bodhichitta">
              Begin by thinking:
            <p>
                I must attain enlightenment to benefit directly each and every living being every day. For this purpose I shall attain a direct realization of the way things really are.
            </p>

        </section>

        <section title="Examination of our Lamrim practice.">

            <p>If our attachment to the things of this life still remains then our renunciation is unqualified.</p>
            <p>If our self cherishing that believes our own happiness and freedom are important while neglecting others freedom and happiness still remains, then this is a sign that our bodhichitta is unqualified.</p>
            <p>If our self grasping that grasps at our self, our body and all other things that we normally see still remains, this is a sign that our understanding of emptiness is unqualified.</p>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Tantra.">

    Everything that exists is merely imputed by mind. The things that we normally see are not imputed by mind. (Therefore they do not exist.)


            <list title="The four seals." comment="The seals are truths and cannot change - they are sealed.">
                <item>All (products) produced phenomena are impermanent.</item>
                <item>All contaminated phenomena are the nature of suffering.</item>
                <item>All phenomena are empty and selfless. (Mahamudra refers to emptiness in the Sutras)</item>
                <item>Only nirvana is peace.</item>
            </list>


        <section title="The Preciousness of Tantra">
            <definition>
                Tantra is defined as an inner realization that functions to prevent ordinary appearances and conceptions and to accomplish the four complete purities.
            </definition>

            <p>Four classes of Tantra - the first three are called 'lower Tantras':</p>
            <list>
                <item>Action Tantra</item>
                <item>Performance Tantra</item>
                <item>Yoga Tantra</item>
                <item>Highest Yoga Tantra</item>
            </list>

                <p>
                    Ordinary appearances (appearances that we normally see) are obstructions to enlightenment and are prevented by clear appearance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ordinary conceptions (holding ordinary appearances to be true) are obstructions to liberation and are prevented by divine pride.
                </p>

                <p>At the beginning, ordinary conceptions are more harmful than ordinary appearances.</p>
        </section>

    <section title="The Tantra of Generation Stage">
        <definition>
            Generation stage Tantra is defined as an inner realization of a creative yoga that is attained through training in divine pride and clear appearance of being an enlightened Deity.
        </definition>
        The main function of generation stage Tantra is to purify ordinary death, intermediate state and rebirth, and to accomplish a Buddha’s Truth Body, Enjoyment Body and Emanation Body.
        <list>
            <item>What is our basis of imputation</item>
            <item>Why we need to change our basis of imputation</item>
            <item>How we can change our basis of imputation</item>
        </list>

    </section>

        <section title=" The Tantra of Completion Stage">
            <definition>
                 Completion stage Tantra is defined as an inner realization of learning developed in dependence upon the inner winds entering, abiding and dissolving within the central channel through the force of meditations.
            </definition>
            <section title="Central Channel">

            The centra channel is pale blue on the outside and has four attributes:
            <list>
                <item>it is very straight.</item>
                <item>inside, it has an oily red colour.</item>
                <item>it is very clear and transparent, like a candle flame.</item>
                <item>it is very soft and flexible, like a lotus petal.</item>
            </list>

            <p>The right channel is red in colour and the left is white.</p>
            <p>The left channel begins at the tip of the left nostril and the right channel begins at the tip of the right nostril.</p>
            <p>Below the navel the left channel curves a little to the right and rejoins the central channel at the tip of the sex organ.</p>
            <p>As The right channel continues below the navel, it curves a little to the left and terminates at the tip of the anus.</p>

            <p>
                The four channel knots occur at:

                <list>
                    <item>the navel channel wheel</item>
                    <item>the heart channel wheel</item>
                    <item>the throat channel wheel</item>
                    <item>the crown channel wheel</item>
                </list>
                At each place there is a twofold know, expect the heart channel wheel where there is a sixfold knot.
            </p>
               <p>The channels are paths through which the inner winds and drops flow.</p>

            </section>
            <section title="An Explanation of Channels"></section>

            <section title="The Indestructible Drop">
                <list>
                    <item>White drops are the pure essence of sperm - its principal seat is the crown channel wheel.</item>
                    <item>Red drops are the pure essence of blood - its principal seat is the navel channel wheel - and it the foundation of the warmth of the body.</item>
                </list>

                <p>The indestructible drop is inside a small vacuole inside the sixfold knot at the heart channel. Upper half red and lower half white - like a small pea - cut in half, hollowed out and rejoined.</p>
            </section>


            <section title="The Indestructible Wind and Mind">
                <p>Inner winds are associated with and act as mounts for various minds. Without inner winds, mind cannot move from one object to another.</p>
                <p>Inner winds are like someone who is blind person but has legs - mind is like someone that has eyes but no legs.</p>
                <p>Minds are always mounted on their associated inner wind, they can both move and see.</p>
                <p>Inner winds that flow through the left and right channels are impure and harmful because they act as mounts for minds of self-grasping, self-cherishing and other delusions.</p>

                <p>
                    Five root winds:

                    <list>
                        <item>Life supporting wind</item>
                        <item>downward voiding wind</item>
                        <item>upward voiding wind</item>
                        <item>equally abiding wind</item>
                        <item>pervading wind</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Five branch winds:

                    <list>
                        <item>moving wind</item>
                        <item>intensely-moving wind</item>
                        <item>perfectly-moving wind</item>
                        <item>strongly-moving wind</item>
                        <item>definitely-moving wind</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </section>

            <section title="An Explanation of Inner Winds">
                <definition>
                     The definition of wind is any of the four elements that is light in weight and moving.
                </definition>
                    The main function of internal winds is to move the mind to its object.
            </section>
            <section title="How to Meditate on the Central Channel">


            </section>
            <section title="How to Meditate on the Indestructible Drop">


            </section>
            <section title="How to Meditate on the Indestructible Wind and Mind">
                Dissolution of the 7 winds. The first 4 winds are gross and the last 3 are subtle.
                A sign appears after the dissolution of each wind. There are 3 levels of dissolution: slight, almost completely and completely. The greater the dissolution - the clearer the appearance of the sign of dissolution.
                <types>
                    <type>The earth wind element supports hard substances in our body i.e. bones, nails. The sign that appears after the the earth wind has dissolved is Mirage-like appearance.</type>
                    <type>The water wind element supports the liquids in our body such as blood. The sign that this wind has dissolved is smoke like appearance - thin blue smoke swirling in a wafting haze.</type>
                    <type>The fire wind element supports the heat in our body. The sign that the fire wind has dissolved is the sparkling fire-flies like appearance.</type>
                    <type>The wind element powers the gross conceptual thoughts that hold appearances to be true. The sign that the wind element has dissolved is the candle flame like appearance.</type>
                    <type>When the wind element dissolves the mind of white appearance arises.</type>
                    <type>When wind mounted by the mind of white appearance dissolves - the mind of red increase appears. Like a red sunlight.</type>
                    <type>When the wind mounted by the mind of red increase dissolves - the mind of black near attainment appears.</type>
                    <type>When the wind mounted by the mind of black near attainment dissolves - the mind of clear appearance arises.</type>
                </types>

            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="The Completion Stage of Mahamudra">

            <definition>Mahamudra Tantra is defined as a mind of fully qualified clear light that experiences great bliss and realizes emptiness directly.</definition>


            <list title="Five stages of completion stage:">
                <item>Isolated body and speech of completion stage.</item>
                <item>Isolate mind - realisation of ultimate example clear light - realises emptiness through a generic image.</item>
                <item>Illusory body of the third stage.</item>
                <item>Meaning clear light - realises emptiness directly.</item>
                <item>Union of meaning clear light and illusory body.</item>
            </list>


            <section>The very subtle wind (continually residing wind) is the very subtle body, which transforms into the vajra body - the pure illusory body which has definite shape and color. For example the vajra body will look like Heruka with twelve arms. The pure illusory body transforms into the form body of a Buddha and the union of bliss and emptiness transforms into the truth body.
            </section>

            <section title ="Great Bliss">
                <list title="Two characteristics:">
                    <item>Its nature is arisen from the melting of the drops inside the central chanel.</item>
                    <item>It functions to dispel ordinary mistaken appearance.</item>
                </list>

                <p>With this bliss, attachment is a cause to be released from samsara. Before we have this bliss - attachment causes us to be reborn in samsara.</p>

                The initial realization of great bliss is the path of seeing of highest yoga tantra - having the power to eliminate both innate and intellectually formed delusions.
                The practitioner arising from this meditation has attained liberation. (Compared to a superior bodhisattva on the path of seeing.)
            </section>
        </section>

    <section title="The Practice of Heruka Body Mandala">
        <section title="The Lineage of these Instructions"></section>
        <section title="What is the Heruka Body Mandala">
            <p>Body refers to our subtle body, our channels and drops.</p>
            <p>Mandala means an assembly of enlightened deities.</p>
            <p>Supporting mandala means the world, environment and palace of an enlightened Deity or Deities.</p>
            <p>Supported mandala means an assembly of enlightened Deities.</p>

            <p>36 channels of our body:
                <list>
                    <item>24 channels of the 24 places of our body</item>
                    <item>4 channels of our heart wheel</item>
                    <item>8 channels of our 8 sense doors.</item>
                </list>
            </p>
            <p>
                Also visualize the red and white indestructible drops at our heart and the 24 drops contained withing the 24 channels.
            </p>
            <p>
            The 24 places of our body represent the 24 places of Heruka in this world:
            <list>
                <item>hairline</item>
                <item>crown</item>
                <item>right ear</item>
                <item>back of the neck</item>
                <item>left ear</item>
                <item>point between the eyebrows</item>
                <item>two eyes</item>
                <item>two shoulders</item>
                <item>two armpits</item>
                <item>two breasts</item>
                <item>navel</item>
                <item>tip of the nose</item>
                <item>mouth</item>
                <item>throat</item>
                <item>heart</item>
                <item>two testicles</item>
                <item>tip of the sex organ</item>
                <item>anus</item>
                <item>two thighs</item>
                <item>two calves</item>
                <item>eight fingers and eight toes</item>
                <item>tops of the feet</item>
                <item>two thumbs and two big toes</item>
                <item>two knees</item>
            </list>
            </p>
            <p>
            Heruka and Vajravarahi (our purified white and red indestructible drops) surrounded by five concentric circles:
            <list>
                <item>4 Yoginis of the great bliss wheel (purified 4 channels in the cardinal directions at the heart channel wheel)</item>
                <item>8 Heroes and Heroines of the heart wheel </item>
                <item>8 Heroes and Heroines of the speech wheel</item>
                <item>8 Heroes and Heroines of the body wheel </item>
                <item>8 Heroes and Heroines of the commitment wheel (purified 8 channels of the 8 sense doors)</item>
            </list>
            </p>

            <p>24 Heroines of the heart, speech and body wheel are the nature of the 24 purified channels of the 24 places of our body.</p>
            <p>24 Heroes of the heart, speech and body wheel are the nature of the 24 purified drops that are contained inside of the 24 channels of the 24 places of our body.</p>

            <p> 4 Yoginis of the great bliss wheel function to bestow spontaneous great bliss:

                <list>
                    <item>Dakini</item>
                    <item>Lama</item>
                    <item>Khandarohi</item>
                    <item>Rupini</item>
                </list>
            </p>

            <p> 8 Heroes and Heroines of the heart wheel function to bestow the attainment of Buddha's holy mind:
                <list>
                    <item>Khandakapaka, Partzandi</item>
                    <item>Mahakankala, Tzandriakiya</item>
                    <item>Kankala, Parbhawatiya</item>
                    <item>Vikatadamshtri, Mahanasa</item>
                    <item>Suraberi, Biramatiya</item>
                    <item>Amitabha, Karwariya</item>
                    <item>Vajraprabha, Lamkeshöriya</item>
                    <item>Vajradeha, Drumatzaya</item>
                </list>
            </p>

            <p> 8 Heroes and Heroines of the speech wheel function to bestow the attainment of Buddha's holy speech:
                <list>
                    <item>Ankuraka, Airawatiya</item>
                    <item>Vajrajatila, Mahabhairawi</item>
                    <item>Mahavira, Bayubega</item>
                    <item>Vajrahumkara, Surabhakiya</item>
                    <item>Subhadra, Shamadewi</item>
                    <item>Vajrabhadra, Suwatre</item>
                    <item>Mahabhairawa, Hayakarne</item>
                    <item>Virupaksha, Khaganane</item>
                </list>
            </p>

            <p> 8 Heroes and Heroines of the body wheel function to bestow the attainment of Buddha's holy body:
                <list>
                    <item>Mahabala, Tzatrabega</item>
                    <item>Ratnavajra, Kandarohi</item>
                    <item>Hayagriva, Shaundini</item>
                    <item>Akashagarbha, Tzatrawarmini</item>
                    <item>Shri Heruka, Subira</item>
                    <item>Pämanarteshvara, Mahabala</item>
                    <item>Vairochana, Tzatrawartini</item>
                    <item>Vajrasattva, Mahabira</item>
                </list>
            </p>

            <p> 8 Heroes and Heroines of the commitment wheel function to pacify our obstacles:
                <list>
                    <item>Kakase</item>
                    <item>Ulukase</item>
                    <item>Shönase</item>
                    <item>Shukarase</item>
                    <item>Yanadhati</item>
                    <item>Yamaduti</item>
                    <item>Yamadangtrini</item>
                    <item>Yamamatani</item>
                </list>
            </p>

        </section>
        <section title="The Preliminary Practices">
            <list title="Four preliminaries:">
                <item title="Going for refuge"></item>
                <item title="Renunciation"></item>
                <item title="Bodhichitta"></item>
                <item title="Guru yoga">
                        <list title="Four purposes of guru yoga">
                            <item>Accumulate merit.</item>
                            <item>Purify negativity.</item>
                            <item>Receive powerful blessings of all the Buddhas.</item>
                            <item>Generate experience of bliss and emptiness.</item>
                        </list>
                      <list title="Five Stages of guru yoga">
                            <item title="Visualization and meditation"></item>
                            <item title="Inviting the wisdom beings"></item>
                            <item title="practice of the seven limbs">
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Prostration.</item>
                                        <item>Offerings.</item>
                                        <item>Rejoicing.</item>
                                        <item title="Purification">
                                                We need to purify:
                                                <list>
                                                    <item>non-virtuous actions</item>
                                                    <item>innappropriate actions</item>
                                                </list>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>Requesting the turning of the wheel of dharma.</item>
                                        <item>Beseeching the spiritual guides to remain for a very long time.</item>
                                        <item>Dedication.</item>
                                    </list>
                            </item>
                            <item title="Making special requests"></item>
                            <item title="Generating the experience of great bliss and emptiness. (definitive guru yoga)"></item>
                        </list>
                </item>
            </list>
        </section>

        <section title="Training in the Generation Stage of Heruka Body Mandala">
            <list title="Five stages of the Yoga of Buddha Heruka">
                <item>
                    Generating the body mandala of Heruka

                        <list title="Three recognitions:">
                            <item>While Experiencing great bliss and emptiness</item>
                            <item>Meditate on clear appearance and divine pride</item>
                            <item>Recognizing the Deities are the nature of our purified channels and drops (subtle body) and the mandala is the nature of our purified gross body.</item>
                        </list>
                </item>
                <item>Clear appearance</item>
                <item title="Divine pride.">
                </item>
                <item>Non-dual appearance and emptiness.</item>
                <item>Mantra recitation.</item>
            </list>
            Concentration on clear appearance makes it easier to develop divine pride or we can contemplate why we can change our basis of imputation from contaminated body and mind to uncontaminated body and mind.
        </section>


        <section title="Training in Completion Stage">
        </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Instructions of Vajrayogini">
        The Yogas of Sleeping, Rising and Experiencing Nectar.

        The Remaining Eight Yogas:
        <types>
            <type>The yoga of immeasurables</type>
            <type>The yoga of the guru</type>
            <type>The yoga of self-generation</type>
            <type>The yoga of purifying migrators</type>
            <type>The yoga of being blessed by heroes and heroines</type>
            <type>The yoga of verbal and mental recitation</type>
            <type>The yoga of inconceivability</type>
            <type>The yoga of daily actions</type>
        </types>

    </section>
    <section title="Dedication"></section>
    </section>
</outlines>

