<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="outlines.xsl"?>

<outlines title="MB">
    <section title="Ultimate Bodhichitta.">

        <section title="Training in Ultimate Bodhichitta">
            <definition>Actual ultimate bodhichitta is a wisdom that directly realizes emptiness motivated by bodhichitta.</definition>

            <p>The knowledge of emptiness is superior to any other knowledge.</p>

        </section>



        <section title="What is Emptiness?">
            Emptiness is the way things really are. It is the way things exist as opposed the the way they appear.
        </section>


        <section title="The Emptiness of our Body">
        <p>
        There are two ways of searching for an object - conventional search and ultimate search.
        </p>
            
        <p>Searching for the body that we grasp - it would exist amongst its parts or outside its parts. There is no third possibility.
        If a part of our body was our body then we would have many bodies. The body is the part-possessor.
        </p>

        <p>
        The collection of the parts of our body cannot be the body. A Collection of parts cannot magically transform into the part possessor - the body.
        If we could find the body as the collection of its parts - then we could remove all its parts and be left with the body.
        </p>

        <p>
        This non-existence of the body that we normally see is the emptiness of our body - the true nature of our body.
        </p>

        <p>
        It is perhaps less confusing to simply say that for a mind that directly sees the truth, emptiness, there is no body. A body exists only for an ordinary mind to which a body appears.
        </p>

        </section>
        <section title="The Emptiness of our Mind">
            <p>
                Our mind is a continuum that depeneds on many factors. E.g. our primary mind is merely imputed upon its basis of imputation - its five mental factors.
            </p>
        <p>
        All phenomena that appear to my mind are the nature of my mind and my mind is the nature of emptiness.
        </p>
        <p>
        This way of meditating on emptiness is more profound then the meditation on the emptiness of our body.
        </p>
        </section>
        <section title="The Emptiness of our I">

        If the I exists in the way it appears then it must exist as one of four possibilities:

        <list>
            <item>as the body</item>
            <item>as the mind</item>
            <item>as the collection of the body and mind</item>
            <item>or as something separate from the our body and mind.</item>
        </list>

        In truth, our self and other phenomena that exist as mere imputation is the ultimate nature of our self and other phenomena, not the conventional nature.
        </section>
        <section title="The Emptiness which is Empty of Eight Extremes">
            <list>
                <item>Production/Disintegration.</item>
                <item>Impermanence/Permanence.</item>
                <item>Going/Coming.</item>
                <item>Singularity/Plurality.</item>
            </list>
        </section>
        <section title="Conventional and Ultimate Truths">
        <p>
            Whatever exists is either a conventional truth or an ultimate truth.
        </p>
        <p>
            Conventional truths ar false objects because the way they appear and the way they exist do not correspond.
        </p>
            Although conventional truths are false, they do exist because they are realised by a valid mind.
            <list>
                <item>Gross conventional truths. Dependence on parts, causes, basis of imputation.</item>
                <item>Subtle conventional truths. Existing merely as imputation by thought.</item>
            </list>
        <p>
            Strictly speaking, truth, ultimate truth and emptiness are synonyms because conventional truths are not real truths but false objects.
        </p>

            <p>When we have realised the mere absence of the eight extremes then we have realised the emptiness of all
                phenomena.
            </p>


            <p>The meditation on the emptiness of produced phenomena(our self who was born in dependence of causes and
                conditions.. ) is called space-like meditative equipoise on emptiness.
            </p>


            If we are successful then during our meditation we are free from manifest self-grapsing.
        </section>
        <section title="The Union of the Two Truths"></section>
        <section title="The Practice of Emptiness in our Daily Activities"></section>
        <section title="A Simple Training in Ultimate Bodhichitta"></section>

    </section>

    <section title="Tantra.">

    Everything that exists is merely imputed by mind. The things that we normally see are not imputed by mind. (Therefore they do not exist.)


            <list title="The four seals." comment="The seals are truths and cannot change - they are sealed.">
                <item>All (products) produced phenomena are impermanent.</item>
                <item>All contaminated phenomena are the nature of suffering.</item>
                <item>All phenomena are empty and selfless. (Mahamudra refers to emptiness in the Sutras)</item>
                <item>Only nirvana is peace.</item>
            </list>


        <section title="The Preciousness of Tantra">
            <definition>
                Tantra is defined as an inner realization that functions to prevent ordinary appearances and conceptions and to accomplish the four complete purities.
            </definition>
        </section>

    <section title="The Tantra of Generation Stage">
        <definition>
            Generation stage Tantra is defined as an inner realization of a creative yoga that is attained through training in divine pride and clear appearance of being an enlightened Deity.
        </definition>
        The main function of generation stage Tantra is to purify ordinary death, intermediate state and rebirth, and to accomplish a Buddha’s Truth Body, Enjoyment Body and Emanation Body.
        <list>
            <item>What is our basis of imputation</item>
            <item>Why we ened to change our basis of imputation</item>
            <item>How we can change our basis of imputation</item>
        </list>

    </section>

        <section title=" The Tantra of Completion Stage">
            <definition>
                 Completion stage Tantra is defined as an inner realization of learning developed in dependence upon the inner winds entering, abiding and dissolving within the central channel through the force of meditations.
            </definition>
            <section title="Central Channel"></section>

            <section title="An Explanation of Channels"></section>

            <section title="The Indestructible Drop"></section>
            <section title="The Indestructible Wind and Mind"></section>

            <section title="An Explanation of Inner Winds">
                <definition>
                     The definition of wind is any of the four elements that is light in weight and moving.
                </definition>
                    The main function of internal winds is to move the mind to its object.
            </section>
            <section title="How to Meditate on the Central Channel"></section>
            <section title="How to Meditate on the Indestructible Drop"></section>
            <section title="How to Meditate on the Indestructible Wind and Mind">
                Dissolution of the 7 winds. The first 4 winds are gross and the last 3 are subtle.
                A sign appears after the dissolution of each wind. There are 3 levels of dissolution: slight, almost completely and completely. The greater the dissolution - the clearer the appearance of the sign of dissolution.
                <types>
                    <type>The earth wind element supports hard substances in our body i.e. bones, nails. The sign that appears after the the earth wind has dissolved is Mirage-like appearance.</type>
                    <type>The water wind element supports the liquids in our body such as blood. The sign that this wind has dissolved is smoke like appearance - thin blue smoke swirling in a wafting haze.</type>
                    <type>The fire wind element supports the heat in our body. The sign that the fire wind has dissolved is the sparkling fire-flies like appearance.</type>
                    <type>The wind element powers the gross conceptual thoughts that hold appearances to be true. The sign that the wind element has dissolved is the candle flame like appearance.</type>
                    <type>When the wind element dissolves the mind of white appearance arises.</type>
                    <type>When wind mounted by the mind of white appearance dissolves - the mind of red increase appears. Like a red sunlight.</type>
                    <type>When the wind mounted by the mind of red increase dissolves - the mind of black near attainment appears.</type>
                    <type>When the wind mounted by the mind of black near attainment dissolves - the mind of clear appearance arises.</type>
                </types>

            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="The Completion Stage of Mahamudra">

            <definition>Mahamudra Tantra is defined as a mind of fully qualified clear light that experiences great bliss and realizes emptiness directly.</definition>


            <list title="Five stages of completion stage:">
                <item>Isolated body and speech of completion stage.</item>
                <item>Isolate mind - realisation of ultimate example clear light - realises emptiness through a generic image.</item>
                <item>Illusory body of the third stage.</item>
                <item>Meaning clear light - realises emptiness directly.</item>
                <item>Union.</item>
            </list>


            <section>The very subtle wind (continually residing wind) is the very subtle body, which transforms into the vajra body - the pure illusory body which has definite shape and color. For example the vajra body will look like Heruka with twelve arms. The pure illusory body transforms into the form body of a Buddha and the union of bliss and emptiness transforms into the truth body.
            </section>

            <section title ="Great Bliss">
                <list title="Two characteristics:">
                    <item>Its nature is arisen from the melting of the drops inside the central chanel.</item>
                    <item>It functions to dispel ordinary mistaken appearance.</item>
                </list>

                <p>With this bliss, attachment is a cause to be released from samsara. Before we have this bliss - attachment causes us to be reborn in samsara.</p>

                The initial realization of great bliss is the path of seeing of highest yoga tantra - having the power to eliminate both innate and intellectually formed delusions.
                The practitioner arising from this meditation has attained liberation. (Compared to a superior bodhisattva on the path of seeing.)
            </section>
        </section>

    <section title="The Practice of Heruka Body Mandala">
        <section title="The Lineage of these Instructions"></section>
        <section title="What is the Heruka Body Mandala"></section>
        <section title="The Preliminary Practices">
            <list title="Four preliminaries:">
                <item title="Going for refuge"></item>
                <item title="Renunciation"></item>
                <item title="Bodhichitta"></item>
                <item title="Guru yoga">
                        <list title="Four purposes of guru yoga">
                            <item>Accumulate merit.</item>
                            <item>Purify negativity.</item>
                            <item>Receive powerful blessings of all the Buddhas.</item>
                            <item>Generate experience of bliss and emptiness.</item>
                        </list>
                      <list title="Five Stages of guru yoga">
                            <item title="Visualization and meditation"></item>
                            <item title="Inviting the wisdom beings"></item>
                            <item title="practice of the seven limbs">
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Prostration.</item>
                                        <item>Offerings.</item>
                                        <item>Rejoicing.</item>
                                        <item>Purification.</item>
                                        <item>Requesting the turning of the wheel of dharma.</item>
                                        <item>Beseeching the spiritual guides to remain for a very long time.</item>
                                        <item>Dedication.</item>
                                    </list>
                            </item>
                            <item title="Making special requests"></item>
                            <item title="Generating the experience of great bliss and emptiness. (definitive guru yoga)"></item>
                        </list>
                </item>
            </list>
        </section>

        <section title="Training in the Generation Stage of Heruka Body Mandala">
            <list title="Five stages of the Yoga of Buddha Heruka">
                <item>
                    Generating the body mandala of Heruka

                        <list title="Three recognitions:">
                            <item>While Experiencing great bliss and emptiness</item>
                            <item>Meditate on clear appearance and divine pride</item>
                            <item>Recognizing the Deities are the nature of our purified channels and drops (subtle body) and the mandala is the nature of our purified gross body.</item>
                        </list>
                </item>
                <item>Clear appearance</item>
                <item title="Divine pride.">
                </item>
                <item>Non-dual appearance and emptiness.</item>
                <item>Mantra recitation.</item>
            </list>
            Concentration on clear appearance makes it easier to develop divine pride or we can contemplate why we can change our basis of imputation from contaminated body and mind to uncontaminated body and mind.
        </section>


        <section title="Training in Completion Stage">
        </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Instructions of Vajrayogini">
        The Yogas of Sleeping, Rising and Experiencing Nectar.

        The Remaining Eight Yogas:
        <types>
            <type>The yoga of immeasurables</type>
            <type>The yoga of the guru</type>
            <type>The yoga of self-generation</type>
            <type>The yoga of purifying migrators</type>
            <type>The yoga of being blessed by heroes and heroines</type>
            <type>The yoga of verbal and mental recitation</type>
            <type>The yoga of inconceivability</type>
            <type>The yoga of daily actions</type>
        </types>

    </section>
    <section title="Dedication"></section>
    </section>
</outlines>

